<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian hnd [sic] sober wish for moderation by a true son of the church.</title>
            <author>True son of the church.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9061</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11906186</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11906186</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50675</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69742)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50675)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 864:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian hnd [sic] sober wish for moderation by a true son of the church.</title>
                  <author>True son of the church.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Moderation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50675:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50675:1"/>
            <p>CHRISTIAN HND Sober wiſh FOR MODERATION.</p>
            <p>By a true Son of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:50675:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50675:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>WHoſe experience in theſe late and ſo long <hi>times</hi> of Faction hath not evidenced to him how ſlight, nay how harſh returns the Aſſertors of truth, and through them truth it ſelf, have ever received from <hi>them?</hi> whilſt men ſo engaged through <hi>blindneſs</hi> or <hi>Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie</hi> (two inſeparable adjuncts to <hi>Faction</hi>) either cannot ſee it as ſuch when propoſed, or ſo far miſapprehend it, as to judge any thing moderate or ſober, to be contradicting or betraying of their Cauſe. I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh that the continuance if not encreaſe of Faction ſtill among us, and its ſad Portents, did not, by ſhewing us the need we have of <hi>Sober Truth,</hi> more then excuſe my expoſing of it to its former fate, by endeavouring to hold it forth upon ſo great diſadvantage.</p>
            <p>But becauſe there is uſually ſo much Modesty as not to fly in the face of Truth, but to ſeek to wound it through the ſides of its Maintainers, and by raiſing the miſts of Prejudice againſt them, to darken the light of Truth it ſelf. I do therefore, to prevent undue Prejudice to my <hi>Perſon,</hi> and thereby to Truth, in the ſincerity of my heart declare. That I am fully ſatisfied with, and devoted to the Government of this Kingdome both Civill as it is a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and Eccleſiaſtick as <hi>Epiſcopall.</hi> That the raiſing of the late War, was at the firſt, exceedingly againſt my Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and was never countenanced or willingly promoted by me to the laſt. In a word, That nothing but a deſire to help towards ſuch a ſettlement of this Nation in Chriſtian Peace and Vnity, <hi>Ut Obedientes gaudeant,</hi> wherein the Subject may delight, hath drawn what followes from me: And I have no other requeſt to you, but that you will come to the reading of it with the ſame unbyaſt deſires, The beſt preparative to a <hi>Sober Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50675:3"/>
            <head>A Chriſtian and Sober wiſh for Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</head>
            <p>THough a particular Deſcription of the late War, &amp; ſucceeding great oppreſſions, under which this Kingdom hath miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſuffered by the ſpace of almoſt twenty years, would be of ſingular uſe to manifeſt our misfortunes who ſeem not yet to be in love with Peace, and to encreaſe amazement in others to ſee us perpetuating Feuds and Ammoſities, when Peace after ſo long confuſion is brought home to us by ſo ſtupendious revolution: Yet ſeeing their deep impreſſions upon mens minds cannot ſo ſoon be blotted out, and it being my deſire to contract my thoughts into as as narrow a compaſs as I may, I ſhall onely give this ſhort accompt of the iſſue of that War, which was the deſtruction of the King (in a manner ſcarce to be paralleld) The change of the form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and thereby the everſion of the Laws; and in their room we were ſubjected to the will and Tyranny of an Uſurper that burthened this Nation: till we diſpairing of deliverance, God brought it to us in his own way, by his Arme: ſo that without the leaſt outward force, without the loſs of one drop of bloud, All weapons fell out of the Armies hands as leaves in Autumne, Our King, <hi>Charles the Second,</hi> (the undoubted Heir to his dead Father) and with him the ancient Government and Lawes reſtored to us, and the ſame face again to the whole Kingdome, without any ſo much as ſigne of oppoſition.</p>
            <p>No man will doubt, much leſſe deny, but that as this wonderful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the Almighty is a Complication of numberleſs Mercies to this nation, and more eſpecially to thoſe therein who having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged on the weaker ſide, were in a low, depreſſed and hopeleſs condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo it multiplies obligations upon us both of <hi>Thankfulneſs, Love, Fear, Obedience, Conſidence towards that God, Who remembred us in our low eſtate.</hi> Pſa. 136.23. And of <hi>Charity, Humanity &amp;c.</hi> towards our Neighbours, and gives cauſe to look upon our ſelves, if we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer not thoſe obligations, in a far greater danger (as having received much greater mercies) then what <hi>Samuel</hi> denounc't againſt the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lietes.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:50675:3"/>1 Sam. 12.24. <hi>Onely fear the Lord and ſerve him in Truth with all your heart: for conſider how great things he hath done for you.</hi> But if you ſhal ſtil do wickedly, ye ſhal be conſumed both ye and your King. <hi>Signal mercies challenge ſignal returns. Signal ingratitude doth draw on ſignal Judgements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not take the task upon me to enter into a ſtrict enquiry how we anſwer God his expectation, in our retributions to him for all his Benefits. I ſhall onely ſo far take notice of the apparent increaſe of <hi>Drunkenneſſe, Exceſſe,</hi> and <hi>Prophaneſſe,</hi> as to appeal to all ſober men whether that reproof be not ſutable to us, which <hi>Moſes</hi> uſed againſt his People, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6. <hi>Do ye thus requite the Lord O ye fooliſh people and unwiſe? Is not he thy Father that hath bought thee? hath he not made thee and establiſhed thee?</hi> But becauſe God is the ſearcher of the heart, I ſhall humbly leave this ſore to his fuller ſearch wiſhing earneſtly for his Grace to enable us ſo, both to examine and Judge our ſelves, that we may not be judged and condemned by him.</p>
            <p>But as to the diſcharge of thoſe great obligations which are thereby laid upon us towards our Neighbours; Who can be ſo inobſervant as not to ſee how Univerſally the Spirit of <hi>Revenge</hi> hath ſpread it ſelf throughout this Kingdom? what repining at the Act of <hi>Oblivion and General Pardon?</hi> ſo far as to uſe that ſcurrile us and diſloyal expreſſion <hi>That it is a general Pardon for all the Kings Enemies, &amp; an Act of Obl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion for all his Friends.</hi> How common are the repetitions of thoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding names of <hi>Rebels, Roundheads, Fanatiques?</hi> (this laſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unreaſonably to any, who are not too extream) What provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in Civil concernments? What ſtumbling blocks in Matters of Conſcience? (though I may grant weak and erring) What ſtiffneſs in things indifferent? as if <hi>Abraham</hi> his example towards <hi>Lot</hi> his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were not to be followed; nor the Precepts of St. <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 12.16. <hi>To condeſcend to men of low Eſtate.</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1. <hi>That the ſtrong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak,</hi> were not to be obſerved. What exaſperations, nay what exaggerations if men ſhal, or ſhal but ſeem to, <hi>Humanum pati,</hi> to ſhew ſome humane frailty? What Indictments are brought upon ſome ſuddain forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs under ſuch Provocations, and with what unuſual violence proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, &amp; with no leſs ſeverity managed? How narrowly do men ſearch to find ſtarting-holes in the Act of <hi>Oblivion?</hi> And ſet others Actions upon the Tenters beyound their true Staple til they crack, to take from them the Bulwark of that Law? Nay how blindly do men run for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge ſake into the very pathes and foot-ſteps of the <hi>Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:50675:4"/>Cromwel, his Mirmydons,</hi> againſt the <hi>Loyal Party,</hi> and ſo imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate them whom they accompt the Peſts of this Kingdom? In a word, what is left untryed to make men deſperate?</p>
            <p>If this manner of proceedings ſhall be examined by the ſtraight rules of mens dutyes as they are Chriſtians, as Men, and as Subjects, I am confident they would appear ſo crooked and unanſwerable in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very reſpect, that Charity leads me to hope, that the unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and danger of theſe eager courſes being thereby manifeſted, will make way for more moderate and ſober Counſels. When therefore I look upon the Law of Chriſt, it is ſo plain in this caſe, that I may well ſay with the Apoſtle. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4: 9. <hi>For as touching brotherly love ye need not that</hi> I <hi>write unto you for your ſelves are taught of God to love one another.</hi> God hath created us all Bretheren, hath therefore ſtamped his Image upon us all; and hath renewed it, when defaced, through Jeſus Chriſt, hath given to us the ſame Law, the ſame Promiſes, and hopes of the ſame Inheritance, hath ti'd us altogether with that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſoluble bond of Love; Made that the fulfilling of his Law. Gal 5.14. the confirmation of our hopes, the earneſt of our Inheritance and the touch-ſtone of our Love to God: without which here, no hope of Union with Him hereafter. 1 <hi>John.</hi> 4.20. <hi>If any man ſay I love God, and hateth his Brother, He is a lyar.</hi> For our Furtherance in this great duty God hath taught us by his own Example. <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>For God ſo loved the World that he gave his onely begotten Son &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and ſent his Son to be the Propitiation for our Sins;</hi> Hath magnified that Grace by owning of it v. 7. <hi>Love is of God;</hi> Hath owned it as his own eſſence, made it himſelf. v. 8. <hi>God is Love;</hi> And from all this grounds our duty v. 11. <hi>Beloved if God ſo loved us, we ought alſo to love one another;</hi> Hath taught us by his Precepts John. 13.34. <hi>A new Commandement I give unto you, that ye love one another, as</hi> I <hi>have lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved you, That ye alſo love one another.</hi> So again <hi>Ch.</hi> 15. v. 12.17. Chriſt there maketh this his Badge, the ſure Mark of his Diſciples. <hi>Ch.</hi> 14.35. <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſciples if ye have love one to another.</hi> And leaſt any ſhould preſume to limit this Vniverſal duty within ſuch bounds as <hi>Intereſt, Malice and Paſſions</hi> of our corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed narrow hearts would preſcribe unto it, God hath alſo taught us, both by his own Act and by his Command, That none, no not our bittereſt Enemyes, are to be excluded from being the Objects of our Love. Rom. 5.8. <hi>But God commendeth his Love towards us in that while we were yet Sinners Chriſt dyed for us ver.</hi> 10. <hi>For if while we
<pb facs="tcp:50675:4"/>were enemies we were reconciled to God by the death of his Son; much more being reconciled we ſhall be ſaved by his life.</hi> Eph. 2.4. To the ſame purpoſe <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44, 45. &amp;c. <hi>But I ſay unto you love your enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, and pray for them which deſpitefully uſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute you, That ye may be the children of your father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: For he maketh his Sun to riſe upon the evil and on the good, and ſendeth raine on the juſt and on the unjuſt.</hi> And to the ſame is that of Luke 6.25. &amp;c. But becauſe every man will be ready to affirm (as uſully they do of faith) That he hath love: give me leave to ſay to him the ſame which St. <hi>James</hi> to ſuch boaſters of faith <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Shew me thy love without thy works, and I will ſhew thee my love by my works.</hi> God hath made his graces fruitful that they may be viſible, and occaſions to glorifie him. <hi>As faith worketh by love, Gal.</hi> 5.6. So love alſo is continually operative; <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Pity,</hi> and their effects flow from it, as light and warmth do from the Sun. Thus hath the love of God manifeſted it ſelf in the redemption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind through the death of his onely Son. Thus Chriſt made his love appear by laying down his life, and commands us, as before, to love our neighbour even as he loved us, and to be ready to give the ſame teſtimony of it as he had done. Commands us not onely to love our enemies, <hi>but to bleſs them, to do good to them, to pray for them, to forgive them.</hi> Matth. 6.14. To give, to lend &amp;c. And from hence are thoſe often Exhortations and Precepts in Scripture to <hi>love, Mercy, Bowels</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Zach</hi> 7.9. <hi>Thus ſpeaketh the Lord of hoaſts, Execute true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udgment, and ſhew mercy and compaſsion every man to his brother.</hi> Rom. 12.10. Be <hi>kindly affectioned one to another in brotherly love,</hi> 14. <hi>Bleſs them which perſecute you,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Pet. 3.8, 9. <hi>Finally be ye of one minde, have compaſsion one of another. Love as brethren, be pitiful, be courteous, rendring not evil for evil, or railing for rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but contrariwiſe bleſsing,</hi> &amp;c. Col. 3.13. <hi>Put on therefore (as the elect of God, holy and beloved) bowels of Mercyes, kindneſs, humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of minde, meekneſs, long-ſuffering, forbearing one another</hi> &amp;c. This is a Principal channel whereby through the whole Scripture, the ſpirit of the Covenant in Chriſt ſeemeth to delight to run. The firſt and ſecond Epiſtles of <hi>St. Iohn</hi> are a continual Eccho of Chriſt his laſt legacy ſo oft commanded in the 13. and 15. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>St. Iohns</hi> Goſpel. But my reſolution for all poſſible brevity enforceth me to conclude this point with that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19, 20. <hi>Dearly beloved avenge not your ſelves, but rather give place unto wrath. Vengeance is mine and I will repay, ſaith the Lord: Therefore if thine
<pb facs="tcp:50675:5"/>enemy hunger, feed him, if he thirſt &amp;c.</hi> Much more to our Bretheren, <hi>Qui eundem Deum ex eâdem lege colunt, etiamſi; forte ſententiis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busdam, aut Ritibus diſſide ant. Grotius de Iure Belli: &amp;c.</hi> who by the ſame Law, worſhip the ſame God, though perhaps they differ from us in ſome Opinions or Ceremonyes.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this may be thought by ſome to be too high a Forme in this corrupted Age, and to ſtrict a rule, to be applied to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of men: let us examine the proceedings before mentioned by thoſe dutyes which lie upon us as <hi>Men;</hi> among which none ſo natural, and therefore indiſpenſable to us as <hi>Gentleneſs, Tenderneſs, Pity, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> towards all Men, and hath therefore obtained the common name of <hi>Humanity,</hi> This I ſay is ſo natural to us that where we are not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by Intereſt or other incitements of Corruption, we do as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and without diſcourſe or uſe of reaſon, exerciſe this virtue, as we do eat, drink, digeſt, and other actions which we performe <hi>Ductu Naturae,</hi> by natural inſtinct. So that to be wanting in this duty is to put off <hi>Man,</hi> nay to fall below the nature of Beaſts for</p>
            <lg>
               <l>— Clementiacunctis</l>
               <l>In ſimiles.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>It may be objected, That ſuch meer natural actions if not guided by <hi>Reaſon</hi> may prove of moſt dangerous concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we may eat (if without conſideration) poiſon <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lay that Rule alſo to them. But becauſe this would open a feild too large for my intended brevity to run over, I will conſine this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination to that great eſſlux and operation of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that Cardinal virtue <hi>(for Moral virtue is but the perfection of Reaſon) Prudence.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be Prudent to grutch at the <hi>Act of Oblivion,</hi> to endeavour to overthrow or in any Meaſure to leſſen the beneſit to any Perſon to whomſoever it is intended, Let His Majeſty give judgement, who accompted it to be a moſt prudential Act in that his gracious Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from <hi>Breda. Apr.</hi> 4. 1660. to prepare way for his reception not onely into his Kingdoms but into the hearts of his Subjects by holding forth his General Pardon to all except onely (as his Majeſty explains himſelf in his ſpeech to the houſe of Peers 27. <hi>July</hi> 1660.) to the <hi>immediate Murtheres of his father:</hi> with this further Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the word of a King. <hi>That no other Crime whatſoever againſt Him or his Royal Father, before the Publication thereof, ſhall over riſe in judgment, or be brought in Question againſt any of them to the leaſt endamagement of them either in their Lives, Inberties or Eſtates or (as far as lies in his power) ſo much as to the prejudice of their Reputations,
<pb facs="tcp:50675:5"/>by any reproach or terme of Diſtinction from the reſt of his beſt Subjects, deſiring, and ordaining, that henceforward all Notes of Diſcord, Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Difference of Parties, be utterly aboliſhed among his Subjects.</hi> His Majeſty acknowledges the great Benefit and Advantage which he had reaped from thoſe his Promiſes and Reſolutions in that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration. <hi>That he did owe his being there in Parliament, to Gods bleſſing, upon the intentions and Reſolutions he then expreſſed to have. That he was perſwaded, if he had not made that Promiſe, neither him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, nor thoſe of the Houſe of Peers, had then been there.</hi> His Majeſty there, and often ſince, acknowledgeth that Love is his great Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and mutual Confidence, the great foundation of it. He well knows,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non ſic Excubiae, nec circumſtantia Pila,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m tutatur Amor, nunquam extorquebis amaci,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hoc alterna Fides, &amp; ſimplex Gratia donat.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No circling Spears, nor Watches ſet by courſe,</l>
               <l>So guard as Love, which thou canſt never force</l>
               <l>From mutual Truſt and Clearneſs, is Loves ſource.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>From this ground his Majeſty ſo often and ſo earneſtly invites both Houſes of Parliament to bring that his Promiſe into an <hi>Act of General Pardon, Indemnity, and Oblivion,</hi> which he there ſaith, <hi>is the moſt reaſonable and ſolid foundation of that Peace; Happineſs and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity which he hopes and prays for to himſelf and all his Dominions, the ſecureſt expedient to prevent future Miſchief, That nothing can more enable Men of dangerous and obſtinate Principles, to do ſo much harm, as the deferring the paſſing of that Act.</hi> And in his Majeſties Speech to both Houſes of Parliament, 29. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1660. He concludes with this, (which He ſaith, <hi>He cannot ſay too often, nor they too often where they go</hi>) <hi>That next to the miraculous bleſſing of God Almighty, and indeed as an immediate effect of that bleſſing, He doth impute the good Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Security that they all were in, to the Happy Act of Indemnity and Oblivion, That that is the Principal Corner Stone which ſupports this excellent building, That creates Kindneſſe in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to each other, and Confidence is our joynt and common Security, That they may be ſure, he will not only obſerve it Religiouſly and Inviolably himſelf, but alſo exact the Obſervation of it from others. And that if any Perſon ſhould ever have the boldneſſe to attempt to perſwade him to the contrary; he will find ſuch an Acceptation from him, as he would have who ſhould perſwade him to burn Magna Charta, cancel all the old Laws, and to erect a new Government after his own Invention and Appetite.</hi> His Majeſty yet
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50675:6"/>further againſt the firſt meeting of the next Parliament, which was 8. <hi>May</hi> 1661. cauſed a Bill to be prepared for the Confirmation of that Act of Indemnity and Oblivion (there being ſome ſcruple of the legality of this preceding Parliament, by reaſon of the Stile of <hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Libertatis Anglia</hi> in the Writ of Summons thereunto) repeated in his Speech to them the ſame words, and tells them, that <hi>He is ſtill of the ſame opinion, and more if poſſible of that opinion then He was, by the experience He had of the benefit of it. That He ſhall never think him a wiſe man who would endeavour to Undermine or ſhake that Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Publique Peace, by infringing that Act in the leaſt degree.</hi> Paſſages of ſo plain and undeniable Reaſon, that to endeavour to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large upon, or explain them, would but leſſen and obſcure them; I ſhall only obſerve upon thoſe his Majeſties irrefragable Principles. That this our <hi>Act of Oblivion,</hi> is the happieſt Copy that ever was drawn from the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Athens: Quae concuſſum &amp; labentem Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatis ſtatum in priſtinum Habitum revocavit.</hi> Which reſtored that ſhattered, and even falling City, to its former Happineſſe and Eſtate. I might add, That it is alſo the beſt parallel to it, whereby upon the return of the People of <hi>Athens</hi> from Baniſhment, and the Miſeries which attended it; and the Ruine of the thirty Tyrants whoſe cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had enforc'd them to it, it was enacted, <hi>Ne qua rerum praeterita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum mentio fieret:</hi> That there ſhould not ſo much as any <hi>Mention</hi> be made of any of thoſe ſad things that had paſſed among them. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to compell men to be <hi>deſperate</hi> be an Act of Prudence, I appeal to every man verſt in any degree of Hiſtory to decide. It have ever been the conſtant and unalterable courſe of all wiſe Commanders to avoid and prevent all occaſions of <hi>Despair</hi> to their Enemies.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Incluſis aperire Fugam, ne pejor in arcto Saeviret Rabies.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To open way for Flight to encloſed Foe,</l>
               <l>Leaſt ſtraitned Rage ſhould thereby fiercer grow.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>And on the other ſide, have often put <hi>neceſſity</hi> upon their own Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as the ſureſt way to give <hi>Valour</hi> the ſharpeſt edge. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſcirent, auxilio ſugae ademto, aut vincondum, aut moriendum eſſe.</hi> That they might know that all means to ſly being taken away, they muſt either overcome, or dye. How ſucceſſeſul this later courſe hath been, doth appear by <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, who had placed his Army (conſiſting but of 34000 Foot, and 4000 Horſe) with the River <hi>Granicus</hi> on their beck, ſo that they could not flye, and thereby overthrew <hi>Darius</hi> with 700000 men. By <hi>William the Conquerour,</hi> who upon his firſt Landing in <hi>England</hi> burnt all his Navy, ſo taking from his Army all hopes of Flight, thereby ſo enflamed their neceſſitated courage, that they became Maſters of the Field, and himſelf of the <hi>Nation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:50675:6"/>How fatal the contrary hath been, is evident by examples which fill all Hiſtories, I ſhall only offer two. The firſt is the moſt famous Victory at the Battel of <hi>Poictiers,</hi> where the <hi>Black, Prince</hi> with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 8000 <hi>Engliſh,</hi> overthrew about 40000 <hi>French,</hi> and took their King Priſoner, who in confidence of his advantages of number, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> denyedany reaſonable terms to the Engliſh, any mediation though of the Pope, and forc't them to extremities: of which Victory, take the confeſſion of a French Author <hi>Froſſard. Qua neſcio an Vetuſt as proferre poſſit clariorem.</hi> I know not whether Antiquity can produce a more glorious. The other is the late Victory of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> over the <hi>Scots</hi> at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> 3. <hi>Sept.</hi> 1650. Where <hi>Ol. Cromwel</hi> having brought an Army of above 20000 to 7000, and of thoſe not above 5000 <hi>ſound,</hi> ſinding his weakneſſe, and having ſlipt his Ordinance, and Sick, marcht to return for <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Scots</hi> having intercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his paſſage, held a Councel and therein admitted ſome Divines, who alleadged that God had delivered <hi>Agag</hi> into their hands, and therefore if they let him go, would require it of them: whereupon they wholly ſtopt the paſſage, and enforc'd the Engliſh to ſight, who now made deſperate, overthrew the Scots Army of 20000 men, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained their paſſage, and returned ſafe and victorious into <hi>England.</hi> This laſt I mention to ſhew that no place or age wants theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and to manifeſt the groſſe error of <hi>Cromwel</hi> in not ſecuring his retreat, an obſervation I received from many of his own Colonels, who therefore, and for ſome other miſtakes, denyed him to be of skill in Conduct.</p>
            <p>What I have before cited by way of Argument out of the Kings own mouth, will ſave much of what might be brought to prove how unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable theſe courſes are to the duty of <hi>Subjects.</hi> Certainly to break or leſſen that which made the <hi>way</hi> ſo ſmooth for his Majeſties return, which conduced ſo much to His &amp; the Parliaments ſafety when retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>which</hi> tends ſo much to the compoſure of mens ſpirits, ſo <hi>much</hi> to the advancement of the Honour and Credit of the King upon theſe His firſt and ſo neceſſary Promiſes to theſe Kingdoms (which if once they ſayl, what foundation can the People ever have to depend upon for their ſafety?) is ſo farr from being agreeable to the duty of <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> in relation to the King, or of <hi>fellow Subjects</hi> in relation to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; that no ſober uninterreſted Perſon but will judge ſuch Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as proceeding from the <hi>Enemies</hi> of them both. <hi>Nothing can lay ſo ſure a foundation towards Univerſal Ruine, as the begetting of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Jealouſies, Fears, Diſpondencies, and Diſtruſts in his Majeſties Royal and Solemn Word and Promiſes.</hi> And therefore I do the more wonder and am unſatisfied, when I conſider the <hi>Perſons</hi> who are ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50675:7"/>forward in theſe wayes of <hi>Violence:</hi> thoſe who term themſelves <hi>Royalliſts,</hi> who would ſeem to engroſſe to themſelves the Title of <hi>faithful Subjects</hi> to the King, and the ſole Care of his <hi>Perſon, Credit, All</hi> who magnifie his Perſon as Sacred, and his Power as Abſolute: to ſee <hi>theſe Men</hi> thus to ſet up their own Intereſt and Spirit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge ſo farr above them both, that there ſhould not the leaſt regard be had by them, ſo little to that his <hi>Declaration</hi> from <hi>Breda</hi> in <hi>April</hi> 1660. either in relation to <hi>tender Conſciences,</hi> or <hi>Purchaſers</hi> upon Publique Sales, or to that his other <hi>Declaration</hi> concerning Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical affairs, in <hi>October</hi> 1660. (that thereby ſome have taken the boldneſſe to ſcatter ſcurrilous papers about <hi>London,</hi> to enquire if any man have found his Majeſties Faith or Promiſe loſt between that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and <hi>Breda</hi>) gives too much cauſe to think that theſe men do mean nothing of what they with ſo much noyſe pretend, that they uſe his Majeſty, but as a ſtale to their Luſt and Intereſt, to which his <hi>Perſon, Power, Safety, Credit, Kingdomes,</hi> All muſt veil or ſignifie nothing. I ſhall to this Point only add that Parallel both of his Majeſties graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deportment, and theſe mens Violence in King <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhai,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. When <hi>Shimei,</hi> who had impudently and maliciouſly curſed <hi>David,</hi> did after meet him returning with Victory to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Abiſhai</hi> ſtirs up <hi>David</hi> to revenge, ſaying <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>Shall not Shimei be put to death for this, becauſe he curſed the Lords Anointed?</hi> Obſerve how <hi>David</hi> takes this motion, <hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>And David ſaid, What have I to do with you, yee Sons of Zeruiah, that yee ſhould</hi> this day <hi>be Adverſaries unto me?</hi> The Greek Septuagint renders it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>inſidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſum,</hi> Treacherous. The Chaldee Paraph, the Syriack, Arabique, and vulgar Latin Tranſlations have it, <hi>Ut ſitis mihi Satan?</hi> That yee ſhould this day be <hi>Satan</hi> unto me? Thus <hi>David</hi> rebukes him as his Treacherous devilliſh Adverſary. The reaſon hereof <hi>David</hi> gives in the ſame verſe, <hi>Shall there any man be put to death</hi> this day <hi>in Iſrael? Do not I know that I am</hi> this day <hi>King over Iſrael?</hi> his return and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration to his Kingdom, was the reaſon why he pardoned <hi>Shimei,</hi> yea <hi>all the men of Iſrael.</hi> And herein doubtleſſe his Majeſtie in the former paſſages hath endeavoured to imitate King <hi>David,</hi> and theſe ſo paſſionate Engliſhmen, do as induſtrouſly follow the pattern of <hi>Abiſhai;</hi> herein only they go beyond him; that we read not after <hi>David</hi> had ſo declared himſelf, that ever the Sons of <hi>Zeruiah</hi> had the confidence to open their mouths againſt it. But theſe men not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the King hath ſo often and ſo fully declared his Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgement towards his Subjects to all the World; yet ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their inceſſant endeavours to fruſtrate all thoſe his <hi>intentions,</hi> to weaken all his <hi>endeavours,</hi> and to break all his <hi>promiſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> In all that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50675:7"/>hitherto hath been ſaid it was ſuppoſed as if thoſe Perſons who are, as before and full of revenge, had conquered thoſe over whom they now ſo much inſult: and truly if they had, yet ſuch carriage, as it is manifeſted to be contrary to <hi>Humanity</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> ſo is it far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the <hi>Magnanimity</hi> of the Romans. <hi>Qui nihil victis eripiebant prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter injuriae Licentiam.</hi> Who took nothing from thoſe whom they conquered but power to rebell. And of that brave Heathen who ſaid, <hi>Armatus ſit oportet quem oderim.</hi> He muſt be Armed whom I hate. But if we ſhould caſt our thoughts back upon the whole tract of our late troubles we ſhall find little ground for them to boaſt of that. Alas, their turning their backs was ſo conſtant that ſome of their Adverſaries might have had the confidence of <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſca,</hi> who willed a drum to be made of his skin after his death in aſſurance that whenſoever it was brought into the feild it would be ſufficient alone to put the Adverſaries to Flight who had ſo conſtantly ſled before him when he lived. And I wiſh it were not too true that ſome of thoſe men have weakned the late Kings cauſe more by their <hi>Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery</hi> then by their <hi>Cowardice</hi> my deſire and reſolution to abſtain from all unneceſſary provocations takes me off from touching fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon this ſtring; or from preſſing how clear an evidence ſuch carriage is of the moſt beaſtly, and loweſt Spirit.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>At Lupus &amp; triſtes inſtant morientibus Urſi.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Wolf and ugly cruel Bear,</l>
               <l>Their very dying Prey do tear.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>How unworthy it is of noble and brave men, let the Scripture judge in that anſwer of the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> to the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 6. When that Prophet had led the great hoaſt of the <hi>Syrians</hi> (whom God at his Prayer had ſmitten with blindneſſe) into the midſt of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> asked the Prophets <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>My Father, ſhall I ſmite them? ſhall I ſmite them? v.</hi> 22. <hi>And he anſwered, Thou ſhalt not ſmit them, would'ſt thou ſmite them whom thou haſt taken Captive with thy ſword and with thy Bowe?</hi> Intimating that it were Cruelty to have done it in cold bloud to thoſe whom he had conquered.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poſt Acis, Odiis idem qui terminus Armis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When Fight is done, all hate muſt ceaſe,</l>
               <l>And with Arms be laid down to Peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Much more where the abſolute hand of God upon them had De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered them into his power. If this be not the preſent caſe, as at the firſt I hinted, I dare appeal even to theſe men themſelves.</p>
            <p>I cannot here omit one Argument, which preſent experience hath
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50675:8"/>brought in theſe few years of this great Revolution whereby is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced even to ſence, how unfit and improbable a way to Settlement theſe Violences are and are like to be, by what they have already effected. <hi>Hand ignota loquer.</hi> I ſpeak but what is to well known. was there ever a clearer day in <hi>England</hi> then that wherein the King ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in his return to <hi>London</hi> 29 <hi>May.</hi> 1660? Was there ever a more enlarged and Univerſal Teſtimony of ſatisfaction and joy, then at that time? Did not many ſeveral judgements and Partyes yet join &amp; emulate in their endeavours for his Majeſties Reſtauration, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment? Did ever Prince offer himſelf to Publick view with more applauſe, or ride, walke, ſwime, and any thing with more ſecurity? Did not this Sereinty continue <hi>till</hi> by the <hi>Act</hi> for eſtabliſhment of the Preſent book? of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and the total neglect of that His Majeſties <hi>Declaration</hi> concerning Eccleſiaſtical Affairs 25 <hi>October</hi> 1660. all hopes were taken from thoſe who (as His Majeſty therein ſaith) had declared themſelves to him <hi>To be neither Enemies to Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, nor Liturgie, but modeſty to doſire ſuch Alterations in either as without ſhaking of foundations might beſt allay the diſtempers which the Indiſpoſition of the time and the tenderneſs of ſome mens conſciences had contracted, from others whoſe conſciences were not ſatisfied with ſet forms till</hi> by ſo vigorous a putting in execution of the Stat. of 35. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. (which was ſcarce ever made uſe of in fourſcore years before) many thouſands were put in fear of Baniſhment for their Conſcience ſake <hi>till</hi> thouſands were caſt into Priſons onely for meeting to ſerve God (at leaſt as they think in a right way) <hi>till</hi> Purchaſers upon Publique Sales found themſelves left to the mercy of thoſe who claimed thoſe Eſtates, and the gracious intentions of his Majeſty in his Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on iſſued out in favour of them made fruſtrate by the Commiſſioners not attending that Service, <hi>till</hi> very many were at ſeveral times upon bare ſuſpicion impriſoned, ſome ſent to remote Caſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thereby bereaved of that part of His Majeſties Declaration from <hi>Breda</hi> which promiſed them <hi>freedome from the leaſt endamagement in their Liberties as well as in their Lives and Eſtates.</hi> But after that in theſe and other things of ſo general and tender concernment ſo great and conſiderable a number of the People, found ſuch diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Expectations though grounded as aforeſaid <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.15. <hi>That they had looked for Peace, but no good came, for a time of Health, and behold trouble.</hi> I wiſh I might not too truly add, After God alſo ſo failed in his juſt expectation from us, for ſuch his unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd Mercies that he might now ſay as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.7. <hi>I looked for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50675:8"/>Judgement but behold oppreſſion, for Righteouſneſs, but behold a Cry.</hi> After theſe uncharitable Violences againſt our Neighbour have been ſeconded with ſuch <hi>open</hi> and <hi>univerſal diſſolution</hi> and <hi>profaneneſſe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, as if we alone had taken upon us to fulfil that Propheſie of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.12. <hi>And becauſe Iniquity ſhall abound, the Love of many ſhall wax cold.</hi> After all this and much more, there is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a ſad and dark Cloud ariſen, and which every day increaſeth, and hath almoſt overſpread the face of our ſo late glorious <hi>Horiſon. How</hi> are mens minds filled with all manner of Fears and Jealouſies? <hi>How</hi> have they broken forth according to the ſeveral apprehenſions and conſtitutions of men, in ſome to deſperate <hi>Attempts,</hi> in others to voluntary <hi>Baniſhment</hi> and <hi>Tranſplantation</hi> of themſelves, their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, Stock, Trades, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in very many to a <hi>Stupefaction,</hi> and ſitting ſtill, to a giving over all manner of employments? what an unheard of deadneſſe is there in all manner of <hi>Trading</hi> over all the Kingdom? (whereof and of the Cauſes his Majeſtie takes notice in his laſt <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,</hi> where he profeſſeth, <hi>That he can never think the Peace of His Dominions ſecure, whil'ſt there ſhall be a Colour left to the Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Diſaffected to inflame the Minds of ſo many Multitudes upon the ſcore of Conſcience, with deſpair of ever attaining any effect of His Promiſes for their eaſe</hi>) His Majeſtie is enforced contrary to his own inclination to continue <hi>extraordinary Guards</hi> for the ſecurity of his Perſon, who can expreſſe what dreadful events ſuch Jealouſies may portend? no man but may in ſome meaſure gueſſe. This I ſay is an Argument whereby the Truth of what was before offered by way of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> is brought down and evidenced to <hi>Sence,</hi> wherein both the Contraries being put together, they do appear as clear, as if written with a Sun beam; ſo that, without the inevitable decree of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ruine both in Church and State be gone out from Heaven, it is impoſſible for us to be poſſeſſed with ſuch blindneſs, and dementati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to forſake ſo plain a path for our future Peace and Settlement, and to follow the other Precipice, whereof every ſtep appears alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be ſo dangerous, and the end deſtructive. God by almoſt a miracle hath put into our hands the power to provide for our future Happineſs and Security, and hath graciouſly put it into His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties heart to chooſe the better part; who hath accordingly ſhewn in his laſt mentioned <hi>Declaration, That he doth and ſhall ever think his Royal Dignity and Greatneſſe much more happily and ſecurely Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his own Clemency, and his Subjects Love, then in their Fears and his Power:</hi> Wherein his Majeſty not only acts according to thoſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50675:9"/>rules of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but from his clear inſight into the nature of his People, who as <hi>Tacitus</hi> obſerves, when under the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Conqueſt of the <hi>Romanes</hi> yet were only <hi>Domiti ut parean, non ut Serviant,</hi> Subdued to obey, not to Serve. The Foundation well or ill laid, concerns exceedingly the whole building; if there be an error or defect in the firſt concoction, it will hardly be rectified by all that follow: That will ſcarce attain to be a true Settlement which is founded upon the Fears, <hi>Jealouſies, Diſlike,</hi> and <hi>Diſſatisfactions</hi> of ſo very many thouſands, eſpecially when grounded upon or accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with thoſe things which concern that whereof no man can be Maſter, <hi>His own Conſcience;</hi> whereof God only can be judge: <hi>Et ſic liberavi Animam meam.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50675:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
